Now, I'm aware that I have this interesting problem
that the audience of this course is a very mixed audience.
Some of you are engineers that are looking to come into the world
of vibe coding and agentic engineering and get pretty hardcore with it.
And some of you are not so technical, might be coming in new to this
and want to use vibe coding as a way to generate code.
So I'm just going to take a minute to talk mostly to the people
that are coming new into this, to level set.
So for people that are already pros,
please put me on 2X, just zip through this part.
I'm also, I've taken a few slides from my MLOps track,
just as a quick briefing for people new to this.
We've been doing stuff this week
that's been using front end code.
And I realized you might not even have the sort of context
of, okay, so I'm sure you've heard terms
like front end and back end a lot, but how does that
actually fit together? We're about to make a project with both a front-end and a back-end.
What does that mean? How does it work? Let me quickly explain. So put simply, the projects
we'll be working on in this course are what they call web applications, meaning that you use a
browser to access them. And it's very common for web applications to have what's called a front-end
and a back-end. There's two parts of the technology. And obviously the front end
is the stuff that runs in the user's web browser. It runs within Chrome or Safari or
Microsoft Edge or whatever. And it's typically got some combination of HTML, which is the
web page, CSS, the style sheets, which controls the appearance, and then JavaScript code running
in the browser that controls the kind of interactivity and the
functionality that runs in the browser in the client on the front end. And then
obviously the backend as you probably know is something which is running on a
server. It's perhaps the thing that served up the web page in the first place,
the HTML and CSS and JavaScript that your browser connected to it to get it.
But also your browser can reach and send messages to the server in order to run
some business logic that could be accessing a database. It might be calling an LLM, and it might
be other APIs you might be calling out to, and you might also have your secrets, your passwords,
perhaps in the.env file, on your backend, on your server. That's the backend. And in terms of the projects we've done this week, the day one
cana teaser was just all front end. Then the cam and board we did on day three, that was also
all front end, all JavaScript served up to the front end. And then what we did yesterday,
it did actually have a backend, but it was also in JavaScript. That was the part that was calling
open router. So you can have front ends and back ends in JavaScript.
What we're gonna do today is gonna have a front end
in JavaScript and a backend in Python,
which is the most common backend programming language
for people working with LLMs.
Because again, going to build an application
using agents that itself is going to call an LLM.
All right, so that's front end versus backend.
And to state the obvious, the way that they are connected
is through these things called
APIs. I'm sure you know this, but the front end makes an API call to the backend. And that's how
it retrieves information it needs to to populate the front end or because the user has pressed a
button that is like a submit button and that is calling an API, back is coming results. And so
that that is the way that front end-end collaborate to solve a business problem.
And all of you, you pros there are like thinking of all the ways I'm oversimplifying.
So feel free to explain it better than me in the Udemy Q&A if you wish.
And just very quickly to dig into the front-end, it's not particularly a big part of this course,
and it's something which I imagine most of you are probably more back-end centric,
and some of you might be front-end devs,
which is, you gotta hate me, for oversimplifying.
But just to give you the layer of the land,
so you know roughly what's going on,
you can have websites that are built
with basic vanilla HTML,
which is what we did in day one,
HTML, JavaScript, CSS,
maybe the JavaScript uses some of the libraries
like jQuery that are really simple, low-level libraries,
not much to it.
But over time, frameworks came along,
which sort of allowed you to build
these interfaces out of components that could update
themselves and react as one of the really big ones,
view, angular, svelte.
These are all popular front-end frameworks
that you see a lot.
And typically, the whole of the front-end
will load as like one request.
And then different components will make different API calls to
repopulate themselves. And when it works that way, it's known as a single page app, an SPA,
and that's very, very common. And there's sometimes written in JavaScript, there's sometimes
written in the typed version, typed script, and both variants exist. And then there are frameworks
like Next.js that's actually created by the company Vercel that is great for deployments.
Next.js is something which sort of packages together,
a bunch of related concerns,
like how to route through web pages,
how to fetch data, how to render things
on either the client or to render them on the server.
All of that is packaged together into next.js.
So it's a higher level application framework.
That is what we've been using for the last few days.
And we'll use it again
today for the front end and it's something that's great and easy. Now I'm a bit of a horror with
React and Next.js. I can do it. I find it really, really difficult. And so for me, using LLM's,
using coding agents has been a lifesaver because they are really, really strong at this. Actually
having said that, I will just give a caveats to that. I do also
see that whilst LMs are very strong at this, they often create websites that look very
similar, web apps that they look a bit like Slop. They have a same kind of look, sometimes
with that purple hue, but you get very familiar with seeing the kind of three icons and that
very standard LMs generated look. And one of the ways that great UX people,
UX UI people really stand out is knowing
how best to organize and communicate information
to make an impact on your user for best outcomes.
And that's where you can still play a role.
So even though when the LM generates a front end,
it can look really great to start with,
you need to go back and push on it
to make sure you get something
that is unique and interesting and good for your users and so on. That's where you can add
the value. Okay, hopefully the front end people up furious with me for oversimplifying.
Remember, you can always add to the conversation. I am now going to do one more bit of foundational
explanation again taken from my Emma Harp's course, which is to introduce Docker that we're going to be using, which is also a great part of
the toolkit for someone who is vibe coding. So Docker is something, again, I imagine 60 to 70
percent of you know it back to front, just a few of you have, I'm sure everyone's heard of
it, not sure what it is. Let me quickly demystify, then we'll install it, and then we will get going
with today's project. So the easiest way to describe Docker
is that Docker gives you a computer within your computer.
It gives you this kind of ring fenced set of resources
that's running on your box in a way
that is isolated from the outside world.
If you know about virtual machines,
it's a sort of lightweight alternative
to virtual machines which are very similar.
That in a nutshell is what Docker is. And so the sort of the so what,
the reason that people love DACA is first of all that it isolates everything inside this little
world so that you can't damage the outside world. And obviously that's something that's
important for for agent coding. It's also super portable that you could build it once and have it
working in one place and then just deploy it somewhere and have it working on one place and then just deploy it
somewhere and have it working over there and so on. There are some footnotes there. It's,
you know, if only life would that easy, but still it's better than many of the alternatives.
It's pretty good for just taking a one, it built once and move it somewhere else and it usually
just works. And there are three concepts to be aware of with Docker with some vocabulary that you get used to in the Docker world.
First of all, there's something called a Docker file.
The Docker file is a file and it's like a recipe.
It's like a set of instructions that describes how you will install stuff and configure stuff on this box within the box.
That's what the Docker file is.
And the Docker file is used to build an image, a Docker image.
A Docker image is like a snapshot of the world.
It's like a particular kind of blueprint for your box within a box
that you'll be able to then use to create lots of these boxes.
That is what the image is, the snapshot.
It's created from a Dockerfile and it's ready for primetime.
And so what is prime time?
Prime time is what's called a Docker container.
A Docker container is made from a Docker image
and the container is an actual live environment,
a live box within your box,
and it's created from an image.
And of course, you probably get the idea,
you could have one image that could create many
of these containers, each container as a little box
within your box and you can have many of them and they all run in this very isolated way. And that's the basics on Docker
and of course there's a, it's at so much, we could say about Docker, I just wanted to
sort of lay the foundations there and for the pros, you know all this stuff already and
never fear we'll be using these a lot more in the next few weeks and we're going to get
much more advanced on this stuff. Okay, and we're now for those that don't already have Doc on your system,
we're going to go and install Docker so that you've got it.
So you go to our website, first of all,
the hard to find website, it's Docker.com.
Go to Docker.com,
and this should come up for you,
and you can see there's lots of stuff here,
and the thing that you want is called Docker Desktop.
That's where you're going to install and check this out.
This is a download docket desktop button
and it's got the different versions
that you might want to download.
And you should download it and run it
and check out the course resources
'cause I'm going to add in if there's anything
that people come across that they're not expecting.
But basically you accept all the defaults.
Don't do anything special.
On a PC it's probably going to prompt you to do it
in a way that involves WSL.
And I would advise you to do that.
Yes, just stick with the defaults, do it its way.
There'll be a bunch of stuff to install.
Do what it says.
Go through all of that.
Everything should get installed.
It's possible you need to restart your computer
to get your path variable updated.
But at the end of it, you should have Docker desktop running.
And when you have Docker desktop running installed,
you should be able to open up and see something like this.
Docker desktop screen that I've got here is like an app.
And on the left here you'll see containers and images.
And this shows you it should be blank for you.
You won't have any.
I have a bunch of images.
Again, the blueprints, the things that have been created
from a Docker file and are ready for prime time.
containers is when they've actually been created.
They are being run.
They are alive.
They are little worlds.
And of course, there's lots of other stuff.
You can have volumes, which is like sort of a ring fenced space storage that could be used by your containers.
So there's lots of detail, of course, but that's the basics.
That's all you need to know for now, because now we're going to go and build a project.